Finding Aid to the Alan Guttmacher Institute records SSC.MS.00720
Sophia Smith Collection
Alan Guttmacher Institute records
1960-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Alan Guttmacher Institute
SSC.MS.00720
20 boxes (20 linear feet)
11.5 linear feet (10 record cartons)
The Alan Guttmacher Institute is a birth control research and advocacy organization; fields of study include abortion, contraception, HIV and STI's, pregnancy and teenage sexual health research. As the Guttmacher Institute website states, 'Good reproductive health policy starts with credible research'; indeed, the Institute's records provide accurate and accessible research from a wide range of sexual and reproductive health fields. Records include reports, data, publications, administrative and financial records, some correspondence. They also include the papers of Jacqueline E. Darroch, Senior Fellow of the AGI and co-author of over 100 publications related to sexual and reproductive health since her involvement with the Institute in 1978. The collection also contains the papers of Christopher Tietze, physician and celebrated researcher of abortion and contraception. [NOTE: All contents list for this collection are not online. Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.] [source: Guttmacher website]
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
Electronic records on the NAS are closed as they contain personal information.
Accruals
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Alan Guttmacher Institute began donating their records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2013. Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
Biographical / Historical
The Alan Guttmacher Insitute (AGI) is a research institution dedicated to the production and dissemination of sexual and reproductive health research. The AGI was founded in 1968 as the Center for Family Planning Program Development, a department of the Planned Parenthood Federation of American (PPFA). The Center had as its champion Alan F. Guttmacher, the prestigious obstetrician/gynecologist/educator who served as PPFA president for more than ten years until his death in 1974. By 1977, the Center was renamed the Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI) in Dr. Guttmacher's honor and incorporated as an independent non-profit organization with its own Board of Directors, distinct from PPFA. But its mission and goals remain the same since its founding. As stated on their Web site, "The Guttmacher Institute advances sexual and reproductive health and rights through an interrelated program of research, policy analysis and public education designed to generate new ideas, encourage enlightened public debate and promote sound policy and program development. The Institute's overarching goal is to ensure the highest standard of sexual and reproductive health for all people worldwide." To that end, AGI maintains an impressive Web site, making widely available the facts and figures of their quantitive and qualitative research published in a range of journals published in a range of journals as well as accessible summaries that highlight the findings of their extensive studies. [source: Guttmacher website]
Related Materials
Associated materials can be found in the Joy Dryfoos Papers and in the Planned Parenthood Federation of America Records.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the administrative files, project record, and publications of the Alan Guttmacher Institute. Records include reports, research data, publications, project files, administrative and financial records, and some correspondence. Since the Guttmacher is an organization that researches and disseminates information on access to reproductive health services, the records especially document various research project and journals. They also include the papers of Jacqueline E. Darroch, Senior Fellow of the AGI and co-author of over 100 publications related to sexual and reproductive health since her involvement with the Institute in 1978. The collection also contains the papers of Christopher Tietze, physician and celebrated researcher of abortion and contraception.
[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online. Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
Birth control -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Birth control -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources; Birth control -- Research -- History -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- History -- Sources; Agendas; Electronic records; Electronic mail; Grant proposals; Surveys; Computer media; Slides; Planned Parenthood Federation of America--History--Sources; Birth control--Research--History--Sources; Birth control--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Brochures; articles; Abortion--History--Sources; Birth control--History--20th century--Sources; Annual reports; Financial records; Writings; Books; correspondence; Dryfoos, Joy G.; Guttmacher, Alan Frank, 1898-1974; Jaffee, Frederick S.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America; Center for Family Planning Program Development -- History -- Sources; Alan Guttmacher Institute; Audam, Suzette; Audam, Suzette
- Guttmacher Institute project records and Jacqueline E. Darroch slides, 2018-S-0046; 4 linear feet (3 record cartons)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes Jacqueline E. Darroch's slides and the project records of Men and Contraception; ACT for Safe Abortion; Managed Care and Opening Doors; and Birth Girls
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Records created and held by the Guttmacher Institute and prepared by Kyra Gilbreath.
  - Managed Care and Opening Doors files, 12 folders (12 folders)
    Biographical / Historical
    Managed Care: The Alan Guttmacher Institute's project Mainstreaming Family Planning in Managed Care aims to document and evaluate how well managed care serves the contraceptive needs of American women, especially those who are poor. The Survey of Women will involve a telephone survey of 1,000 women enrolled in managed care plans across five states.
    Opening Doors: Low-income and minority women have greater difficulties than other women in avoiding unplanned pregnancy; in part, this reflect lower levels of contraceptive use and higher likelihood of contraceptive failure. However, it is not clear whether racial and ethnic differences simply represent the greater socioeconomic disadvantage of black and Hispanic women or if they result from other characteristics of or barriers faced by these women. This study sought to learn directly from low-income women about their perceptions of and experiences with contraceptive methods and contraceptive service providers. Using that information, a further goal of this project was to inform policymakers and those providing contraceptive and other reproductive health information and services to women about how they might better meet the needs of low-income women and minority-group women. The key objective of this project was to document the attitudes and experiences of low-income women and minority women with regard to obtaining contraceptive information and services and effectively using available contraceptives.
    Background information was prepared by the Guttmacher Institute to be sent in with the materials.
    Materials include publications, surveys, findings, proposals, meeting notes, field notes, and correspondence related to the Managed Care and Opening Doors projects.
    - Managed Care article drafts and 3 surveys, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Managed Care findings and drafts, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Managed Care data: coding, keypunching, 1997; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Managed Care questionnaire development, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Managed Care Kaiser proposal revision, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Managed Care survey methods group, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Managed Care advisory panel meeting, 1997 December; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Opening Doors copies, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Opening Doors focus group transcripts, 1995-1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Opening Doors field reports and correspondence with MDI, 1994-1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Opening Doors original charts, 1995-1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Opening Doors preliminary figures, 1995 November; 1 folders (1 binder) (Box 2)
    - Opening Doors questionnaires and open-ended responses, 1995-1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Reassessing United States Family Planning and Reproductive Heath Needs research files, 15 folders (15 folders)
    The ultimate goal of this project is to reduce the level of unintended pregnancies in the United States. This project uses a variety of data collection and analysis activities designed to monitor family planning clinics and the clients they are serving.
    Materials include research plans, surveys, correspondence, mailings, clinic records, CDC services and records, and client data.
    - Family planning needs and assessment papers, 1994-1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Letters from reporting systems, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Women at risk 1995 papers, 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - CP needs and services mailing, 1995-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Clinic census directory sources and fieldwork records, 1994; 5 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Client clinic data revisions, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Family planning clinic information and articles, 1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Family Planning Clinic Services in the US, 1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Indian Health Services directory, 1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - 300 ACT Sharing Responsibilities, "ACT for Safe Abortion", 5 folders (5 folders)
    "The ultimate goal of this project is to increase women's access to safe abortion services, by compelling decision-makers to act by generating the political will to make abortion safe, legal, and available. The project's specific objectives are:
    Increase the quality and quantity of accurate high-priority information on abortion care available to policymakers and key stakeholders through research, the publication of a global chartbook, at least two journal articles and a range of communications products (fact sheets, policy briefs, PowerPoint presentations, etc.) in order to advance evidence-based discussions and policies; and through assessment of knowledge gaps and research needs in the Buffett Foundation's 11 priority countries leading to preparation and submission of proposals to address identified high priority questions and issues. Communicate/disseminate findings and materials to global, regional, and local audiences to reinvigorate policy discussions on clandestine abortion and advance evidence-based policies at all levels. Project components: The monograph included a literature review of the past 10 years of evidence about the safety of abortions and included analysis of Guttmacher's AICM projects in select countries that had recent project activity including: Guatemala, Nigeria, Pakistan, Philippines, Uganda, Burkina Faso, Ethiopia, and Mexico."
    Background information submitted with the materials by the Guttmacher Institute.
    Materials include the article published in the Women's Heath Journal, proposal and earlier communication, PRB/Guttmacher meeting information, and reviewer comments.
    - Women's Health Journal article and other final articles, 2007; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - 300 ACT proposal and earlier communication, 2007; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - PRB and Guttmacher meeting in New York materials, 2007 November 20; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Unintended pregnancy article reviewer comments, 2010; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Journal submission invitations, 2010; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - "Men and Contraception" article and research, 11 folders (11 folders)
    Final Article: Young Unmarried Men and Women Discuss Men's Role in Contraceptive Practice Authors: David Landry and Theresa Camelo Published in 1994 by Guttmacher Institute in Family Planning Perspectives (now Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health) Description of the Study: "This research entails a series of focus groups designed to explore men's involvement in decisions regarding contraceptive use. It is one component of a project designed to begin to assess future directions for research regarding men and their attitudes and experiences regarding sexuality and contraceptive use. The project also includes a meeting of experts to discuss current and needed research regarding men and a special report summarizing research needs."
    Background information included in the materials written by the Guttmacher Institute
    - Men and Contraception MAC proofs/IRB, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Article submitted to Family Planning Perspectives, outside reviewers, exec staff, SRAs, and SA, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Articles and focus group studies, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Proposal and budgets, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Focus group report and summary, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Bibliography information, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Men and Contraception meeting information, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Internal memos, meeting notes, and grant announcements, 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Birth Girls files, 16 folders (16 folders)
    Files for "A California Study of Why Young Women Carry a Pregnancy to Term"
    Principal Investigator: Jennifer Frost, Dr. P.H.
    Project Description: "As part of The California Wellness Foundation's (TCWF's) Teenage Pregnancy Prevention Initiative, the Alan Guttmacher Institute is undertaking an investigation into issues surrounding teenage childbearing in California. Key questions that underlie this project include: Why do so many adolescents become pregnant and why do those who do so accidentally (the great majority) carry their pregnancy to term rather than have an abortion? What can be done to emphasize preventive behavior, what services are available to assist teens facing a pregnancy; and what factors, life circumstances and parental, peer or partner pressures are involved when teens decide to carry a pregnancy to term?"
    Background information included in materials sent by the Guttmacher Institute
    Materials include notes and paper drafts, proposals, survey development, information on counties and prenatal care providers, correspondence, and final documents.
    - Notes and paper drafts, 1997; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Survey development papers, 1994-1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Santa Cruz County information and notes, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Phone/fax survey of prenatal care providers, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Early paper drafts, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Planned Parenthood of Mar Monte correspondence and notes, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Final documents for survey, approximately 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Birth Girls final report, 1999; 3 folders (1 folder and 2 booklets) (Box 2)
    - California Wellness Foundation: correspondence during grat, 1996-1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Early analysis files, approximately 1997; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Memos related to articles and distribution, 1998-2000; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire development, pretest questionnaires and comments, 1996; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - California Birth Girls proposal, 1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Birth Girls revised files, 1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Jacqueline E. Darroch slides, 6 folders (6 binders)
    Darroch's bio from Guttmacher's website, Guttmacher.org: "Jacqueline E. Darroch is a Senior Fellow at the Guttmacher Institute. She has been involved with the Guttmacher Institute since 1978. As Interim President in 2003 and Senior Vice President from 1996 to 2004, she provided leadership for the organization's policy-focused research and public education on sexual and reproductive health. She oversaw developments and opportunities in the areas of research, theory and methodology, health care delivery and financing, public opinion and behavior, and local, state, federal and international policies and programs. In addition, she worked to obtain funding from private foundations, the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development and the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services' Office of Population Affairs. Dr. Darroch also held the positions of Director of Research (1978–1988), Vice President for Research (1988–2002) and Vice President for Science (2002–2004). Dr. Darroch served as Associate Director for Reproductive Health at the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation from 2004 to 2006. She is the author or coauthor of more than 100 articles and publications on sexual behavior, fertility, family planning, maternal and child health, teenage pregnancy and abortion."
    This box contains slides of presentations given from possibly 1990-1997 by Jacqueline E. Darroch (formerly Jacqueline Darroch Forrest). Some of the binders in these boxes contain handwritten notes regarding the order of the slides etc.
    - Bright red binder, "Unintended Pregnancies: Why are there so many?", approximately 1990-1997; 1 items (1 item) (Box 3)
    - Large navy blue binder, multiple lecture topics, approximately 1990-1997 (Box 3)
      - U.S. Women's Perceptions of and Attitudes about the IUD J.E.D. -Long-Acting Hormonal Contraceptives in the United States J.E.D. -The Value of Contraception Felicia H. Stewart MD (OPA) -What U.S. Data Tell Us Now about Norplant- 1995 National Survey of Family Growth- J. Darroch Forrest -Handwritten note on Jacqueline Darroch Forrest stationery -What We Learned from the 1995 National Survey of Family Growth J.E.D. -Unintended Pregnancy: What is it and What difference does it make? J.E.D. -Women's Interest in Microbicides J.E.D. and Jennifer J. Frost -State Estimates of Annual New STD Cases J.E.D. -Unintended Pregnancy: What is it and what's behind it? J.E.D.
    - Black binder with metallic spine, multiple lecture topics, approximately 1990-1997; 1 items (1 binder) (Box 3)
      -An Epidemic of Anti-Abortion Violence in the United States- David A. Grimes MD, Jacqueline Darroch Forrest, Alice L. Kirkman, Barbara Raford
      -Family Planning and Planning Families: An International Comparison Elise F. Jones, Jacqueline Darroch Forrest, Stanley K. Henshaw, Aida Torres -Who Fits into the "Second Transition?"- Jacqueline Darroch Forrest -Abortion Update: Medical Aspects of Pregnancy Termination -WHO-The Risk Approach in Health Care (no title slide, but slides themselves are labelled with this) -Health Care in the United States Jacqueline Darroch Forrest -Risk and Responsibility: Teaching Sex Education in America's Schools Today 1989 The Alan Guttmacher Institute
    - Black binder 1, multiple topics, approximately 1990-1997; 1 items (1 binder) (Box 3)
      -begins with slide 91-001 Abortion rates, 1987 by income (no title page) -two titles slides: Contraceptive Use and Access to Services: Needs of Low-Income Women and Sexual and Reproductive Behavior in the United States (both J.D.F.)
    - Black binder 2, multiple lecture topics, 1992; 1 items (1 binder) (Box 3)
      -The Life Cycle and Contraceptive Needs: The thirties and beyond J.D.F. -Why Isn't Every Pregnancy Planned? J.D.F. -Stages of Women's Reproductive Lives: Times for IUD or Norplant J.D.F. -some incomplete collections of slides -title slide Epidemiology of Unintended Pregnancy and Contraceptive Use J.F.D. -Twenty-Third Ortho Annual Birth Control Study 1991
    - Red binder, "Clinical Trials", 1993; 1 items (1 binder) (Box 3)
      -no title slide, but note "93-001-027 War [Women at Risk]  Win [Women in Need] ests-SPPA" -Demographics of Barrier Contraceptive Use J.D.F. -Oral Contraceptives -maybe Epidemiology of Unintended Pregnancy and Contraceptive Use J.F.D. -Sex and America's Teenager- The Alan Guttmacher Institute 1994 -Paper items tucked into the back of the binder… "The History of Contraception Museum" and a chapter about the menstrual cycle -Hand written note "1994"
- Guttmacher Institute research files, staff files and project records, 2018-S-0052; 7.5 linear feet (6 record cartons)
  Records created and held by the Guttmacher Institute and prepared by Smith student intern Kyra Gilbreath.
  These records include notes, proposals, meeting information, drafts and critiques, correspondence, literature related to Guttmacher Institute projects, budgets, background information, data analysis, and statistics relevant to projects.
  - Dr. Jacqueline E. Darroch's Files on Contraceptive Methods, 7 folders (7 folders)
    Jacqueline E. Darroch is a Senior Fellow at the Guttmacher Institute. She has been involved with the Guttmacher Institute since 1978. As Interim President in 2003 and Senior Vice President from 1996 to 2004, she provided leadership for the organization's policy-focused research and public education on sexual and reproductive health. She oversaw developments and opportunities in the areas of research, theory and methodology, health care delivery and financing, public opinion and behavior, and local, state, federal and international policies and programs. In addition, she worked to obtain funding from private foundations, the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development and the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services' Office of Population Affairs. Dr. Darroch also held the positions of Director of Research (1978–1988), Vice President for Research (1988–2002) and Vice President for Science (2002–2004). Dr. Darroch served as Associate Director for Reproductive Health at the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation from 2004 to 2006. She is the author or coauthor of more than 100 articles and publications on sexual behavior, fertility, family planning, maternal and child health, teenage pregnancy and abortion.
    This box contains selections from Dr. Darroch's files on contraceptive methods. These are folders containing correspondence, Guttmacher internal memos, handwritten notes, and publications authored by Dr. Darroch. Much of what is here discusses the controversy surrounding early IUDs and the potential consequences of pulling IUDs from the market.
    - Norplant correspondence and product info, 1989-1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Non-Cp Hormones, 1985-1993; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Alza correspondence, company, and product information, 1987-1991; 2 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - End of IUD background information, 1986; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - IUD articles and correspondence, 1980-1987; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - End of IUD article, 1985-1988; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - March of Dimes 1991, 10 folders (10 folders)
    "The March of Dimes (MOD) and The Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI) have agreed to seek funding for a national project on availability, accessibility and use of prenatal care. A proposal will be prepared during 1991, submitted to foundations and/or the March of Dimes grants committee, with the expectation that if funds can be raised for this project, work will begin in early 1992.